software engineering radio episode 30
architecture part 3
[Music]
okay welcome to episode I don't know
which episode but it's actually the
third part of the architecture series of
episodes in software engineering radio
in the last episode on software
architecture we talked about the
different quality attributes of which
you have to strike a compromise when
building a software system in this
episode we want to show you some of the
basic tools that us the architect have
available when building software and
also show some of the relationships of
those basic techniques to the quality
attributes we introduced in the
preceding architecture episode and by
the way it's again Marcus and Michael
doing this episode and as last time we
decided that we'll do it only in a pair
without Alexander because finding a time
slot where the three of us have time is
impossible so so architecture as we
probably mentioned before is basically
not something that's formal but it's
rather based on heuristics and Michael
you probably want to elaborate somewhat
on this topic yeah unfortunately there's
really no formal rules or things like
that for a developer when he architect
or designs a piece of software it's much
more based on on experience what has
been working before by others and by the
person himself to a large extent to me
at least it's also gut feeling at some
point in time you don't really think so
so hard anymore about it and you just
know well for this kind of job you you
just need for example a pipes and
filters to sign because otherwise it
just doesn't make sense so so it just
this experience gets then like intrinsic
and into your daily actions and
decisions to read about what work
fathers
there are patterns and and the whole
literature about software architecture
and patterns is a it's a great source of
resources and and experience and we'll
put some of those links into our flow
notes before we go into detail just one
last introductory thing if architecture
is based on heuristics and experience
then as a kind of reverse consequence
what you have to do is obviously you
have to test your architecture early on
like if you have your gut feeling that
says if I do it this way it's gonna be
scalable then it's probably good for
your job position for your resume and
probably also for your stomach too to
make sure you test that early in the
development in the preparation of this
episode markers you show the special
kind of basic mechanisms of architects
basic properties of software
architectures what are those so the
basic mechanisms that you have available
as an architect or as a developer when
building system is basically for its
separation abstraction compression and
sharing and we'll elaborate on each of
them in some detail and then also take a
look at a couple of derived mechanisms
they then have terms like coupling and
you're probably sure knows cohesion
information hiding right but we'll come
to that later right so let's start with
the basic mechanisms of software
architecture and and again just to
mention it's not about the basic means
of how you as an architect you know
called an a determinant and stuff it's
really about technically building the
system so I guess I'll do the first one
right said okay for you
it's alright okay so the first one is
separation also known as locality and
the idea is that you put a specific
functionality into a distinct module or
artifact and you give it a well-defined
interface so if you do that then this
obviously simplifies changes to that
functionality because the implementation
is hidden behind the well-defined
interface which hopefully
change it also enhances your chances for
reuse because if you have a piece of
functionality or a responsibility as
people often say modularized into a
specific artifact or component or
whatever then it's easy to reuse that
well-defined piece of functionality at
least in theory we all know that reuse
is kind of the holy grail it also helps
to decompose complex problems because
you can solve subproblems in separate
modules or whatever and then solve the
more complex problems by reusing or
using the solutions and the modularized
solutions for the smaller problems it
also simplifies parallel development
because different people can define
different artifacts and only communicate
through their well defined interface a
negative consequence is that it might
decrease performance because you have
interactions in the system and it also
might cause problems with regards to
teamwork because if you have many
different parts of your system isolated
from each other then you probably have
different sub teams and communication
between those teams is often somewhat of
a problem so if we consider how
separation influences the quality
attributes then it increases
maintainability because you separate
things into separate modules it also
increased increases the reusability we
explained that in a before why
portability is also increased because
you might have a separate module that
captures all the specifics of a platform
and by exchanging that one you can port
to another environment actually this is
called the microkernel architectural
pattern and we'll discuss architectural
pattern in a future episode testability
is also increased because you can test
each of those well-defined modules
separately scalability might be
increased because you can separate or
exchange some of the modules with us
more scalable or with modules that are
more suitable for the changing
environments and as we said it might
decrease performance
so let's take a look at a number of
examples for separation one is of course
in procedural programming you have sub
programs sub function sub procedures the
named parameters and return type are the
interface and you can call those sub
programs or procedures from various
locations and you can reuse them in
object-oriented programming we have
classes the whole point of classes is
being that they are a module of
functionality a piece of responsibility
and obviously the operations and if you
really want to do this the data
structures define the interface is
typically the operation of the public
operations define the interface the
inflammations implementations typically
private another way of separating things
is components and of course nobody knows
what a component is but for our purposes
we say that a component is a piece of
well-defined functionality that exposes
this functionality you through a
well-defined interface and also
specifies the dependencies so the
interfaces it uses as part of its
contract a fourth example is aspect
orientation what you do there is that
you take things that are not modular
risible with the means that I explained
before like sub programs classes and
components and separate those out into
what people call aspects and then you
take some infrastructure typically
called an aspect Weaver to weave in
those separated aspects into your base
program and again that's something where
we already had the interview with Craig
or coach Alice and also it's a topic
that we'll cover in more detail in the
future the second basic mechanism is
abstraction and abstraction and in
general is about hiding details it's
about modeling it's about removing
details and hiding them it's about a
more general view of a problem that is
factored out and just leaves
I would leave some details for later
resolution the basic consequences of
that is basically that it simplifies
client programming that a
the users of a certain artifact don't
have to worry about all the
configuration and parameter passing
details that it basically can provide a
simplified programming model for clients
also it enhances the chances for reuse
if things are simpler if there are not
so many details exposed the chance for
reuse is larger further it helps to
understand complex problems it because
it hides complexity it makes things
easier to understand and as I just
mentioned easier to reuse easier to
grasp as a developer but on the other
hand hiding things introduces another
layer of indirection this is funny
another layer of indirection somebody
said all the pattern all the bought
patterns are about is just another layer
of indirection well I don't think that's
true but for some patterns it's it's the
point yeah so regarding the
relationships to the quality attributes
of course hiding complexity hiding
details improves maintainability because
the the implementer of that artifact can
then later change the details without
the clients noticing that same thing for
reusability for portability usability
which is the discussed that it's easier
programming model typically that for
example applying the facade pattern you
can hide a complex API you can hide
configuration complexities and make
things simpler but performance is really
there's negative impact there examples
of abstraction include inheritance and
super classes where a client can work
with a reference to a superclass and and
it just doesn't have to care about the
concrete class so inheritance and
superclass
our one example and here the client
Subic Li has to know only to superclass
and the subclasses then implement all
the details of which you could have
actually multiple implementations for
example using the strategy pattern where
you would have done multiple
implementations of the same interface
University or C++ templates is also
something where you abstract an
algorithm and leave out the details of
the data type another example is the
factory pattern where you would delegate
responsibility to create configure blump
together the component to the factory
abstract from the creation details right
and another abstraction example is
domain-specific languages right so in
this case you you identify a certain
viewpoint with regards to your system
and then you only describe those aspects
of the system that are relevant to that
viewpoint in the DSL and then you use
the usual means we talked about in the
model driven development episodes to
create a runnable system from that so
the main specific languages are also a
very powerful way of abstracting out
details the next basic tool of the
architect is compression which is
basically the opposite of separation the
ideas instead of separating things from
each other and having separate modules
with separate interfaces you join
certain things this obviously increases
the performance because you have less of
your layers of indirection it might it
might speed up the development time that
depends a little bit the point is of
course if you create a lot of chaos
because you can't separate things nicely
then your development time will only be
sped up in the first couple of weeks and
maintainability will go down and of
course it increases the accidental
complexity accidental complexity
accidental complexity is a term that
says that there is complexity that you
could avoid if you would organize your
system in a more suitable way as opposed
to inherent complexity
which is basically a consequence of your
functional requirements so examples for
compression is for example in lining if
your compiler removes function calls and
directly copies the function body to the
call side then a level of indirection is
removed and your performance will
increase and we have the other negative
consequences of course in case of
compiler inlining you don't care because
the bytecode or the generated machine
code is not something you care about
as long as it's fast another way is
macros and some forms of generic
programming specifically C++ templates
where macros directly replace source
code by other pieces of source code
again instead of calling things
indirectly so macros are could be called
could be considered to be some kind of
source level inlining other examples
could for example be if you have a nice
database layer using for example
hibernate that abstracts all kinds of
details from your database and makes
things portable you can exchange things
it does your object relational mapping
and of course sometimes the performance
you get from that approach is not good
enough and you might embed SQL code
directly in your source code of course a
lot of negative consequences but the
performance might increase because you
compress a lot of different levels of
indirection and you can get better
database performance compression is
something and that is really important
that should be done automatically
because otherwise the disadvantages
usually become too problematic and also
compression is typically used as a means
to improve the performance of a system
and as we all know premature performance
optimization optimization is a bad thing
so you should only optimize for
performance once you actually measured
that there is a performance problem at a
certain location in your code and that
as a consequence means that you should
compress things only if you can't if you
notice that compression will improve
performance
basic mechanism that we want to discuss
is resource sharing and resource sharing
is when you encapsulate data or services
centrally with associated resource
manager basically share you resources
among multiple clients that access them
to either communicate or trigger each
other the consequences here are the
increase the consistency in your system
of course having some having a central
resource that's easier than to align
multiple distributed resources that of
course that also decreases performance
because it's very easy to design a
bottleneck in your system the
relationships to the quality attributes
are as follows integrability is improve
because you have a central point where
you can configure your system you have a
central pool of resources for example
where you can do the optimizations
maintainability is improved you don't
have to address multiple resources
multiple locations but you have a
central location where you can do the
maintenance performance as we just
discussed is impacted negatively some
examples here include pooling
patterns for example thread or memory
pools yeah we talked about that in the
resource management episode exactly and
also Singleton's but Singleton's are in
most cases bad so i don't elaborate on
that and then the the next thing that is
very typical that our these are
blackboards and databases so-called also
shared data repositories where all
clients all system components would
access those resources to get their
configuration to get the shared state
information from and the last one our
servers in typical client-server
interaction systems where the servers
offer central resources central services
to all involved clients right and just
to reiterate on that if you have
multiple clients accessing a shared
resource concurrently you're getting
into all those problems with locking and
we talked about that in the concurrency
episodes or a Michael do you want to
mention two words on that one yeah here
there are some typical patterns on how
to avoid that for some of the money - a
pattern is the easiest one just log
everything on every operation as soon as
a client enters it so that you ensure
that only one client operates in your
central resource but with that of course
you you have the the strongest the
liabilities here and it's typically
quite inefficient so there are more
advanced topics but please listen to the
concurrency episodes they will they had
discussed it in the past and will
discuss it in the future even more right
so after those basic mechanisms will now
take a look at some of the derived
mechanisms that are probably a bit more
well-known with regards to the terms we
use those are decomposition and
delegation information hiring decoupling
and separation of concerns
right so um you're gonna start yeah
decomposition it's the the basic or
another term here is divide and conquer
something very elementary and in
computer science that you have a problem
you have an algorithm and you separate
it into smaller problems and you
delegate your subproblems and into
subcomponents you you separate your
problem into multiple ones this is based
on separation and abstraction as the
back basic mechanisms and here you have
your responsibility that you associate
with multiple implementation artifacts
and the classical examples are
procedural decomposition strategy
pattern or Oh in general the things we
all know the next one also well-known is
information hiding it basically says
that clients can only see some aspect of
the artifact and other artifacts are
hidden it's also based in separation and
abstraction and of course the idea is
that the clients depend only on those
public on the visible aspects or parts
and the private parts can be changed
without the clients noticing the
coupling between the clients and the
provider is obviously reduced so again
the most well-known example for this
thing is classes classes have a number
of typically a number of private
attributes private operations as well as
number of public operations which form
the interface and of course you can also
separate the interface out even more by
explicitly defining an interface
depending on whether your technology
allows you to define interfaces and also
some of the things we mentioned before
abstract classes factory strategy
pattern again our way is of hiding
certain aspects for example the aspect
of which implementation is used or in a
certain context which implementation of
a strategy is used in a certain context
the next item is decoupling and as we
all know coupling is bad for maintenance
reasons coupling to responsibilities
that actually don't belong together that
that aren't the same responsibilities
just induce introduces complexity which
we can avoid so decoupling tries to
reduce the dependencies among the
responsibilities assuming the
responsibilities are done encapsulated
in individual classes and and components
and usually an interface at least the
interface and its implementation are
separated but here we also discuss about
general responsibilities having then
them separated into individual artifacts
this is based on separation and
abstraction as basic mechanisms and
typical implementation examples here
include delegation or strategy factory
and but to me also the general
architectural work of decoupling
identifying responsibilities checking
whether they depend on each other
whether they have to depend on each
other and then decoupling those
responsibilities into separate
subsystems classes components whatever
is relevant in your context right and
the way you typically do that is by
identifying the responsibilities you
have to take care of in your system and
then group together those
responsibilities which you know interact
a lot with each other and decouple those
others which have fewer interactions
that's probably the the core the core
idea here
yeah great model for that are the glass
responsibility collaboration short just
the CRC cards and I thought I think that
it was introduced by Ward Cunningham yes
I think so
the first time and there's a nice paper
where we put the reference into the show
note which explains on how how to work
with CRC cars and to me that is true
architecture because I don't have to I
don't think about technology I don't
think so a whole lot about interfaces
and communication and data
I just think about responsibilities pure
responsibilities collaborations giving
good names for those responsibilities
moving down them around until you get a
the gut feeling that this is just right
how the responsibilities our side
well the gut feeling you can also
measure you should minimize the
dependency yeah and you should decouple
them burn necessary and put things
together where they belong together
that's actually very interesting because
what you talk about is something that I
like to call functional architecture
where you really take the set of
responsibilities of assisted them and
assign them to classes or components or
whatever the other kind of architecture
is what people often call a technical
architecture where the problem is more
or now you have sort of the functional
architecture how do you get it solve all
your inner T's right so how do you
technically build your system so that it
performs well or so that it scales well
also that it's maintainable and
sometimes you have to make compromises
with regards to your functional
architecture if you have distributed
your responsibilities nicely and you you
see that things are distributed and
therefore slow then you might have might
have to change things I think
you agree Michael that for us it's
really important to distinguish also the
conceptual architecture and the
technological realization right that at
least and what you just described I I
would suggest a two step approach here
first a functional architecture then try
to come up with an ideal technical
architecture but then soon met the the
functional architecture - the technical
architecture and then think about the
technologies that you might use to
implement your architectures something I
really like to ramble about is that if
you go to conferences or talk to people
and talk about architecture people very
often come up with things like oh you
know we have this web service based
architecture or we have this EJB
architecture and people always talk
about technologies instead of concepts
instead of saying hey we have an
architecture which uses a component
model with those properties as well as
an asynchronous communication based on
XML or whatever people always talk about
technology that's really annoying yeah
and we'll have another episode on this
thing in the future so next is
separation of concerns Marcus yeah I
think that's also the last one so the
idea is that you separate common and
reuse the parts of a system that can be
implemented generically which is often
some of the technical architecture
concerns into some kind of reusable
asset that is later integrated with
functional concerns which implements the
concrete application that the kind of
typical example for this thing is the
application server the application
server in an enterprise system takes
systems takes care about you know
transaction security persistence all
that stuff scalability to some extent
and the application server provides
these things as services that you can
use as an application developer and you
don't have to re-implement them and the
consequences of using this thing is that
the technical concerns can be
implemented once and can be reused and
the developers of the functional
concerns thing we just talked about
before you know with the COC cards and
stuff don't have to care about
technical concerns too much I think this
is really a very important thing
application servers and frameworks are
one way to tackle it aspect orientation
is another one model driven development
is yet another one where you describe
your functional requirements are
actually the functional algorithms your
your your your application logic in in
some kinds of models and yet then you
have generators that generate code in a
way that implements the non-functional
requirements - okay I think this kind of
concludes this episode Michael anything
else you want to say or some outlook you
want to give on on the subsequent
architecture episodes so the next
episode on software architecture will
cover the topics on architectural styles
and patterns right and another episode
after that one will take care of how to
kind of make sure an architecture is
followed and implemented consistently in
large teams in large systems and then
even further in the future we'll take a
look at product lines so this finishes
this episode thanks for listening
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at se - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think Software
Engineering radio wants to thank Henning
poly for the intro and outro music as
well as Lipson for providing the
bandwidth this episode of se radio as
well as all other episodes is licensed
under Creative Commons license see the
software engineering radio website for
details